<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-06-16T15:27:46+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Robotics Lab URJC</title><subtitle>Programming Robot Intelligence</subtitle><author><name>Enrique Shinohara</name><email>enriqueshino@gmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">Week 0</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/weekly%20log/week-0/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Week 0" /><published>2022-06-15T00:00:00+02:00</published><updated>2022-06-15T00:00:00+02:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/weekly%20log/week-0</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/weekly%20log/week-0/"><![CDATA[<p>Ready, set, go!</p>

<p>With this first entry on my weekly blog, I start my master’s thesis with the objective and hope to learn and solve problems related to autonomous driving using computer vision. This first week, the focus is pointed towards installing and playing with softwares such as <a href="https://classic.gazebosim.org/download">Gazebo</a> (a simulator where we can test our robots virtually) and <a href="http://wiki.ros.org/noetic/Installation/Ubuntu">ROS</a> (Robot Operating System). The installation was pretty straight forward, given that both softwares are currently only officially supported for Ubuntu, the instructions can be followed in their respective homepages.</p>

<p>Finally, we needed to undertand how we were going to do a blog for our thesis. For this, thanks to the feedback provided by my thesis tutor, it was decided to write the blog with Github Pages which start static servers to host website directly from our Github repository. In order to mess with this function I had to clone the following repositories:</p>

<ul>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/JdeRobot/jderobot.github.io">jderobot.github.io</a>: repository of the website of the association of Robotics and Artificial Intelligence, JdeRobot.</li>
  <li><a href="https://github.com/mmistakes/minimal-mistakes">minimal-mistakes</a>: repository of the minimal mistakes Jekyll theme for Github Pages.</li>
</ul>

<p>Both of them having multiple examples in order to know and test functionalities, on my own, of Github Pages and Jekyll Templates for an aesthetically pleasing blog website.</p>

<p align="center">
<img src="/assets/images/minimal_mistakes.png" width="300" />
</p>]]></content><author><name>Enrique Shinohara</name><email>enriqueshino@gmail.com</email></author><category term="Weekly Log" /><category term="github page" /><category term="ros noetic" /><category term="gazebo" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Ready, set, go!]]></summary></entry></feed>